<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Skip the Viking]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Software Architect Journeyman]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 12:40:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Contact Me]]></title><description><![CDATA[Freelancer? Consultant? Contractor? YES! Professional Experience I’ve automated onboarding systems for enterprise resource planning systems…]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com/contact/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https:/www.skiptheviking.com/contact/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 23:15:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Freelancer? Consultant? Contractor?&lt;/em&gt; YES!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Professional Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve automated onboarding systems for enterprise resource planning systems.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve built interactive webapps for generating reports, monitoring complex systems,
and producing scientific output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve built ETL pipelines transforming manufacturing data into databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve written simple automated scripts in a day that replaced daily manual tasks for perpetuity saving THOUSANDS of man hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backends, frontends, middleware, you name it…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a pretty good chance I can solve your IT/ Software / Data problem.  And if I can’t, I can usually give you a good idea
of who can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I desperate for work? Not even close. I have no shortage of work.  But if you have an interesting problem
that needs to be solved or just some consulting on how to do something, contact me and we can set something up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to hire me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:skip&quot;&gt;skip@skiptheviking.com&lt;/a&gt; what you need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let’s set up a call&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How much do you charge per hour?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t charge hourly (&lt;a href=&quot;/code-hooker&quot;&gt;see code prostitution&lt;/a&gt;).  I charged based on value (my time and yours).  Is this automation going to save your company
20k per year? Would you be willing to spend 5k to get it in production? You get a deliverable for a fixed price and I get to
leverage my industry knowledge to build it for you as efficiently as possibly.  We all win.  This only works if your requirements
are clear (or at least mostly clear - in software requirements ALWAYS evolve).  We can talk more about this. But send me an email and let’s see
if we can come up with a arrangement&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Professional Book Recommendations]]></title><description><![CDATA[Professional Book Recommendations I read BOOKS. A lot. From people who know their shit. Yes, I learn a ton working and from personal…]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com/books/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https:/www.skiptheviking.com/books/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 23:15:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/fddbf/myLibrary.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 35.69444444444444%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAHABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEDBP/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAGLALIFP//EABgQAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIDEQAB/9oACAEBAAEFAgdicUJvb//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABcQAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARQTH/2gAIAQEABj8CTNpD/8QAGxAAAgMAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAVEAESExQWH/2gAIAQEAAT8hPi15AMK46g1dF1P/2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEIvf/8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAFB/9oACAEDAQE/EMR//8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQEQ/9oACAECAQE/EAuf/8QAGhABAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhAFFhMf/aAAgBAQABPxCvoaOlubhxyklVfAusfoAEqCscz//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;My Library&quot;
        title=&quot;My Library&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/88218/myLibrary.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/7237a/myLibrary.jpg 148w,
/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/0cfdf/myLibrary.jpg 295w,
/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/88218/myLibrary.jpg 590w,
/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/77d57/myLibrary.jpg 885w,
/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/5a917/myLibrary.jpg 1180w,
/static/01c296f2a8660fa47d4814a1adfacf2e/fddbf/myLibrary.jpg 2880w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professional Book Recommendations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read BOOKS. A lot. From people who know their shit. Yes, I learn a ton working and from personal experience. But books
allow you to learn from OTHER people’s experiences, often decades more experience.  It’s awesome when you can find a good mentor,
but when you read BOOKS you can acquire yourself some of the best
mentors in the industry for a nominal price by reading there most comprehensive thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some of my book recommendations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;#x26;camp=1789&amp;#x26;creative=9325&amp;#x26;creativeASIN=0132350882&amp;#x26;linkCode=as2&amp;#x26;tag=skiptheviking-20&amp;#x26;linkId=6649d19eb218bc766ae4b5cb570efe61&quot;&gt;Clean Code&lt;/a&gt;
by Robert C. Martin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want to write clean code? You cannot go wrong with this book. Robert C. Martin
aka Uncle Bob has one of my favorite writing styles.  And he has 50 years (50 YEARS!!!!) of writing code
experience, so you cannot go wrong with his advice.  It is tried and true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;#x26;camp=1789&amp;#x26;creative=9325&amp;#x26;creativeASIN=0132350882&amp;#x26;linkCode=as2&amp;#x26;tag=skiptheviking-20&amp;#x26;linkId=6649d19eb218bc766ae4b5cb570efe61&quot;&gt;The Effective Engineer&lt;/a&gt; by Edmond Lau&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;START with this book if you want to be an effective engineer.  This is a red pill / blue pill scenario.  If you want to know
how things are done right, read this book.  Or stay in the matrix and
keep with the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/37MwiFT&quot;&gt;The Systems Bible&lt;/a&gt;
by John Gall&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A MUST read.  Before you build software you must understand SYSTEMS. What do I mean by systems?
Everything is a system.  And all systems have inherent properties.  Every system wants to expand
to fill the known universe.  Only simple systems work.  Complex systems that work only work because
they are composed of simpler systems.  These principles and much more are found in this book
in often humorous (but true) examples.  You won’t be able to put this one down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2urvesI&quot;&gt;Clean Architecture&lt;/a&gt;
by Robert C. Martin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want clean architecture? Invert your dependencies towards least change. How do I know this? This book!
Another hit from Uncle Bob - this is a must read if you want to design a system that is flexible and maintanable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/37S86SS&quot;&gt;The Maxwell Leadership Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I’m getting religious on you. This is the NKJV version of the bible with commentary
from John C. Maxwell, one of the best writers on leadership.  I have yet to read one thing
from his commentary that hasn’t helped me in the workplace be a better leader.  Remember, leadership
and management are different things.  Not everyone is a manager, but everyone ought to &lt;a href=&quot;/first-raid&quot;&gt;be a leader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[High Class Code Prostitution]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last summer I was applying for new jobs (something I do regularly, more on that later).  As usual, people 
love my resume so we set up a…]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com/code-hooker/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https:/www.skiptheviking.com/code-hooker/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 23:15:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last summer I was applying for new jobs (something I do regularly, more on that later).  As usual, people
love my resume so we set up a time to talk.  Except I’m not talking with the customer.  Nor am I talking with
any of the engineers.  I’m talking with the “talent acquisition” portion of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TA: So are you a software architect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: Well yeah, I design and build software.  That term is thrown around a lot,
can you be more specific on the context?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TA: No that’s great, the customer wants the person to be a software architect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TA: So do you know Java?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: Yep, I just spend the last year and half building ETL systems in Java that are being used in production
and helped meet mission critical needs. What particulars are you looking for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TA: Ok great, yeah, they want someone who knows Java&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;em&gt;And so on and so forth, they continued to ask questions about “skills” that I might have
because that’s what the customer wants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the end they want to hire me and we start talking salary.  Now
they wanted to hire me as an employee because employees are more “loyal” (barf - loyalty is earned by being loyal to your employee -
not based on the payment arrangement).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they wanted me to work on site in their office.  But there customer was remote in another city. And the team I’d be working
with were also in other cities.  So I’d have to relocate to work on site in the office, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;TO THEN WORK REMOTELY&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m already feeling like they want a whole lot and are giving very little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I start asking about the business model, and it’s all too familiar.  The “business” finds a customer who needs some
software built, system upgrading, etc…  basically some sort of “service”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So they hire someone else to provide that service.  They charge the customer rates of 250, 300, even 500 an hour - and pay the engineer
somewhere between 40 - 60 an hour (sometimes lower…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it dawned on me what other business follows the EXACT same business model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prostitution!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “business” is the pimp, the “customer” is the customer, and I get to be the code hooker!!! Yay!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized my current job was this model, and pretty much every job I was applying to was this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, all the interview questions might as well be “are you a blonde? They want a blonde” And I’m dying my hair blonde er
ugh updating my resume to reflect some trait that particular job wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean I’m freaking software engineer! I solve problems in software for a living! And I’m good at it! Is it really that important whether
I’ve worked with the exact set of esoteric technology that your company uses at that point in time? I mean half the shit they list
on job descriptions they don’t even do.  Don’t even get me started on scrum…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line, I realized my job hopping was just upgrading pimps.  Long term, I need to get into a different business model.  Business don’t just use software
like the use toilet paper, for a lot of businesses, software IS the business.  Don’t believe me? How long could the business run if all the software and data
was destroyed? This has happened before and those businesses were shutdown for good the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For something of that value, I want to be a partner.  I want to build software that helps the business be successful, and share in the profits.  Almost
all other creative professionals have some sort of royalty on their creative work.  Software engineers have been taking only a small cut of their actual
value.  And when we bill hourly, we are only incentivitized to waste time?!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this blog is part of my long term goal to not be a code hooker, but rather an owner.  I want to own my source code I write, reuse it to help businesses,
and come to a win win solution where the business does better and I do better!  If you need someone like that then &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact me!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Design a tax estimating app]]></title><description><![CDATA[Conceptual Design Originally, I wanted to create a REST service that would receive the input of someone’s tax data and return the output of…]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com/tax-estimator-design/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https:/www.skiptheviking.com/tax-estimator-design/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2020 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Conceptual Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, I wanted to create a REST service that would receive the input of someone’s tax data and return the output of it’s calculation.  This design would allow
me to reuse the tax estimator service among a web app, ios and android app, and any other services. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After working on the app I decided to run the calculations client side.  Mainly, at this point in the development,
I’m just going to have a web app.  And since this is not currently yet persisting data, I can build the app
without a backend. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Technical Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taxes are a funny thing.  You have gross income, modified adjusted gross income, adjusted gross income, and taxable income.  It gets really tricky
when you are married calculating separate FICA’s, passive losses, and student interest.   And don’t get me started on rental income…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, initially I was build an entity named TaxDataInput that I could pass to a control
object called TaxCalculator to calculate theproper numbers.  But I found this design taking
far too long.  Java double primitative’s were hard to test (for currency assmptions they are awful),
so of course I switch to the BigDecimal.  Even then I found myself converting doubles into BigDecimal and back into
doubles to do calculation.  The syntax was verbose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead wrote a quick model in javascript, and chained computed values together.  While this
is technically causing redundant computations, it runs instantly in the browser. So for the development speed I moved my
model to the front end and now I am able to develop much faster.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why I won't let my doctor wife work]]></title><description><![CDATA[For those of you with a spouse working, 
how much money are they really bringing into the family? You might think whatever the paycheck is…]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com/why-I-wont-let-my-doctor-wife-work/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https:/www.skiptheviking.com/why-I-wont-let-my-doctor-wife-work/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For those of you with a spouse working,
how much money are they really bringing into the family? You might think whatever the paycheck is,
and you would be wrong come tax time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you might think they are taxed at your marginal tax rate. Again, you would be wrong. As was I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, I was given the opportunity last year to work additional hours at my company
for additional pay.  And my doctor wife who works PRN (as needed) also controls how many hours
she works. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now my additional hours were not time and half - just paid time. And my wife’s PRN hours are just
a normal rate as well.  But like many in our generation, we are always looking for a side hustle to
try to get ahead (or catch up - however you want to look at it)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, one day I took the time to understand how much of the additional hours we were working
were getting taxed.  After I conducted the analysis - I didn’t come in for extra hours one more time.
Nor did I have my wife work any more PRN hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Hidden taxes.  Or as I long to call it, the REAL marginal tax rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would you work weekends if 90 percent went to the government? How about 50 percent? Well,
it came out to be about 45 percent for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can this be? I must making a killing to be in such a high tax rate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope.  Not really.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The First Raid]]></title><description><![CDATA[When the emissary’s came to the Viking lands and
asked to speak to their leader, the Viking responded: “We are all leaders here”. And this…]]></description><link>https:/www.skiptheviking.com/first-raid/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https:/www.skiptheviking.com/first-raid/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 23:15:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When the emissary’s came to the Viking lands and
asked to speak to their leader, the Viking responded: “We are all leaders here”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is exactly how Software Engineers need to be.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve stumbled across Skip the Viking, a software architect journeyman
who is on a “raid” to become a master software architect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why architect and not just engineer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There shouldn’t be much of a difference in terms of skill set, but an
architect takes ownership of the design of a system.  And should be working
at a higher scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I’ve seen people hide behind the title architect to mean
they no longer have nuts and bolts technical skills.  That is not me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write code. Lots of code. And I’m constantly trying to become a better programmer.  Check
out my library &lt;a href=&quot;/books&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  And yes, these are affiliate links, so if you buy one of these books I’ll get paid.
Good, that means you can help me stop being a &lt;a href=&quot;/code-hooker&quot;&gt;code prostitute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>